<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue of dying wel. First written in the Italian tongue, by the reuerend father Don Peeter of Luca, a chanon regular, a Doctor of Diuinitie and famous preacher. VVherin is also contayned sundry profitable resolutions, vpon some doubtful questions in diuinitie. Translated first into French, and novv into English</title>
            <title>Dottrina del ben morire. English</title>
            <author>[Pietro da Lucca].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 109 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114608</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849833</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849833</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15004</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15004)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1113:3, 1349:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue of dying wel. First written in the Italian tongue, by the reuerend father Don Peeter of Luca, a chanon regular, a Doctor of Diuinitie and famous preacher. VVherin is also contayned sundry profitable resolutions, vpon some doubtful questions in diuinitie. Translated first into French, and novv into English</title>
                  <title>Dottrina del ben morire. English</title>
                  <author>[Pietro da Lucca].</author>
                  <author>Verstegan, Richard, ca. 1550-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By A. C[onincx],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at Antwerp :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of a French translation by Pierre Frizon of: Dottrina del ben morire.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: R.V., i.e. Richard Verstegan.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page engraving.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6802 on UMI microfilm reel 1349.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Bodleian Library and the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1113 (Bodleian Library copy) and at reel 1349 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15004:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15004:1"/>
            <p>A DIALOGVE OF DYING WEL.</p>
            <p>Firſt written in the Italian tongue, by the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend father Don Peeter of Luca, a Chanon regular, a Doctor of Diuinitie and famous preacher.</p>
            <p>VVherin is alſo contayned ſundry profitable reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, vpon ſome doubtful queſtions in Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated firſt into French, and novv into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>VVatch and pray for you knovv not vvhen the tyme is. <bibl>Mar. 13.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at Antwerp, by A.C. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15004:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15004:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT REVEREND, LADY IOAN BARKLEY, ABBESSE of the Engliſh Monaſtery of Nunnes of the holy order of <hi>S. Benedict,</hi> in Bruxels.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Reuerend, I heer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent vnto your peruſal this dialogue of dying wel, a woork more of woorth for the goodnes then in value for the greatnes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15004:3"/>It was firſt written in the Italian tongue by a deuout Chanon of <hi>Luca,</hi> &amp; by <hi>M. Peeter Friſon</hi> a deuout Chanon of <hi>Rhemes</hi> (wel knowne through his pietie vnto many of our nation) it was ſince tranſlated into french.</p>
            <p>The remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death as Biſhop <hi>fiſher</hi> (of bleſſed memory) was wont to ſay, doth neuer come out of ſeaſon, and this ſpake that good father in regard that the remembrance of death tendeth vnto a care to endeuour to dy wel, a matter of moſte important conſideration vnto all that liue.</p>
            <p>There are ſundry ſerpents and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that out of filth and corruption do take their originals, and ſo in lyke man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner was that vgly monster, called <hi>death;</hi> out of the filth and ſin of our firſt aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, firſt engendred. The agillitie &amp; arte of this moste mercileſſe tyrant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in the continual caſting of deadly dartes,
<pb facs="tcp:15004:3"/>
and infynit hee throweth out, euen in euery moment, neuer ayming but at ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing hartes, neuer miſsing thoſe hee ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth at, neither is there any armour to bee found that may withſtand his hart-pierſing force. VVherefore ſeeing to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd death there is no remedy, the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy then that remayneth, is the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning how to dy wel: this leſſon the enſuing dialogue teacheth, only truants neglect to learne it, but attentiue ſchollers do deepely imprint it in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory.</p>
            <p>To your good Ladiſhip I dedicate the ſame: vnto you the firſt Abbeſſe of your holy order reuyued in our nation, whoſe poſteritie by the diuine prouidence may come to brighten our country with their ſhyning ſanctitie as your predeceſſors heretofore haue donne: after that <hi>S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne</hi> had brought and taught vnto the Engliſh people the firſt knowlege &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15004:4"/>
belief in the true God and his deer ſonne and our Sauiour, Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
            <p>A religious man was this firſt Apoſtle of ours, and of your order, as alſo were thoſe holy Abbeſſes and religious virgins ſo much come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by the venerable Bede and other veritable writers, in there relating their holy liues and wonderful miracles, yea euen after their deathes, which were true arguments of their dying wel, the which they wel learned to do whyle they liued, as he graunt wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may to whoſe holy tuition I leaue your Reuerend Ladiſhip. This 3. of April <hi>1603.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladiſhips very much deuoted <hi>R. V.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="proem">
            <pb facs="tcp:15004:4"/>
            <head>THE AVTHORS PROHEME.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>CCORDING</hi> to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Ariſtotle, man of all mortal creatures is moſte prudent, for that hee alone foreſeeith thinges to come, and therefore differeth from the brute beaſt, which regardeth only thinges that bee preſent.</p>
            <p>Man therefore ſeeing hee muſt dy, is by his natural wiſdome enclyned to foreſee his death, the cogitation wherof is vnto him a thing more terrible, then any other thing els what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, and it much more doth importe him.</p>
            <p>He therefore that deſyreth to walk wiſely in this miſerable lyfe, muſt in ſuch ſorte pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare and diſpoſe himſelf for dreadful death, that when it approcheth neere vnto him, hee be not taken vnprouyded, and that for want of
<pb facs="tcp:15004:5"/>
due conſideration he loſe not the chief felicitie, and beſydes that be aſsigned for euer vnto the paines of hel. VVherefore beeing deſirous to begin this diſcourſe of the arte or ſcience to dy wel: for an introduction thereunto I preſuppoſe ſuche an imagined nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as heer enſueth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15004:5"/>
            <head>A DIALOGVE OF DYING WEL.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE was a marchant which trauayling into a far countrie, as hee wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred out of his way, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to come into a great wilderneſſe, where he chaunced to meet with an old Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, who through great age was euen ouerſpent &amp; worne: with whome after he had bego<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne to enter into diſcours he aſked him what he did their in that ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie place, now ſo neere vnto the date of his death. The Eremite anſwered &amp; ſayd. Thow ſhalt (my ſonne) vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, that when I was in the flouriſhing age of thirtie yeares, I forſook the deceitful world, and retyred my ſelf into this ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litarie place, heer to do ſome kynde of penance for my former ſynnes, and to
<pb facs="tcp:15004:6"/>
learne to dy, and heere haue I conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuallie dwelt in ſolitude theſe threſcore and ten years. Then the Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſaid to him, it ſeemeth too mee a thing very ſuperfluous that thow ſhouldeſt ſeek to learne to dy, ſeeing thow (beeing a mortal man and alreaddie an hundred yeers old) muſt needs dy, and that verie ſhortly. The Eremite anſwered, this is that which I feare &amp; not without great aſtoniſhment do euerie day think vpon, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that I am not redy for death, and neuertheleſſe I know aſſuredly that I muſt dy.</p>
            <p>To this then quoth the Marchant: what thing is it to know how to dy? The old Ermite anſwered him: to know how to dy, is no other thing, then to flie all things that may offend our lord God, and with diligence to doe all that hee comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth, obſeruing obedientlie all his preceptes and commandements, and to be in ſuche wiſe neat and cleane in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, that arryuing vnto the laſt end of our lyfe wee may be receaued into the euerlaſting reſt of the cittizens
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15004:6"/>
of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. At theſe woordes the Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t begining to feel in his hart ſome ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the change of his lyfe, ſayd vnto him againe, o deere father, your talk greatly pleaſeth mee. Tel mee I beſeech yow, could yow giue mee ſome good inſtructions touching this moſte neceſſarie point of dying wel? Hereu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the Ermite anſwered that he was very willing to make him partaker of ſuch gaine as alredy himſelf had gotten by his ſtudy in that ſcience, &amp; there-with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al aſked him what trade hee liued by, hee anſwered that hee was a Marchant, whervnto the Ermite added: that the arte of a Marchant is to ſel his marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe deer; and to buy good cheape: yf thow then deſire (quoth hee) to make a good market, and to buy a treaſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable, and far beyond all eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for a litle price, behold heauen which is ſo great and glorious, and buy it with thy temporal goods, giuing them to the poore for thee loue of God.</p>
            <p>Then thee Marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t beeing deſirous
<pb facs="tcp:15004:7"/>
to bee further ſatisfied, aſked him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, ſaying, o deere father and my good maiſter, I pray yow tel mee, yf ſo be that you had a ſcholler, whome you loued wel, or a ſonne, whome you deerely affected, what arte principallie would you teache him? The Ermite anſwered: ſetting a ſyde all ſecrets, all artes, all experimentes and all ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the world, other arte would I not inſtruct him in then in the arte to dy wel, becauſe it excelleth euerie other ſcience, theſame being more neceſſarie, more profitable and more worthie, then the others, as without the which a man cannot purchaſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, nor eſcape the horrible paynes of hel. Theſe other artes do teache to diſpute, to talke, to meaſure, to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to ſing, and ſuche like exerciſes, which are all of litle value, and only vſed of men whyle they liue in this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable and tranſitorie lyfe, but the arte to dy wel, teacheth thee to get paradiſe, where each ſcience, and all kynde of knowledge is to bee found: By thee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15004:7"/>
artes, thow ſhalt get wordlie glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and earthly ſubſtance, which moſte ſpeedely paſſeth a way: but by the arte to dy wel; is gotten the glorie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which endureth for euer, by this arte is our ſoule ſaued, and wee haue this life onlie to the end, to learne the arte to dy wel. To this our lord Ieſus Chriſte doth inuite vs, in many places of the goſpel: as where hee ſaith:<note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> 
               <hi>Eſtote parati quia neſcitis diem neque horam,</hi> that is to ſay; Bee ye in a reddines, becauſe ye know not the day nor the hower. Againe:<note place="margin">Luc. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Eſtote parati quia qua hora non pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis filius hominis veniet,</hi> that is: Be ye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared becauſe the ſonne of man wil come what hower ye think not. To come to this knowlege the ſaincts and true philoſophers haue taken great tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uail and paynes, becauſe this ſcience a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone helpeth more then all the other together. In this day and night the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie fathers did exerciſe themſelues, and now euerie good religious perſon and true deuout Chriſtian putteth all his ſtudie to learne to dy wel: yea hee is
<pb facs="tcp:15004:8"/>
not a true chriſtian, neyther can be cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led a wiſeman which doth not procur ſome meanes to learne this ſo worthie and ſo neceſſarie a ſcience, without which, none can dy wel, nor conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently be ſaued. For as ſainct Bernard ſaith, <hi>venientem mortem nemo bene excipit, niſi qui ſe ad ipſam dum viueret, bonis operibus preparauit,</hi> that is, No man doth wel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue death, but hee that while hee li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, did prepare himſelf for it, by good woorkes.</p>
            <p>The paſſage of death beeing then more perilous then any other thing (for as muche as that therein either is loſt the ſoueraigne good, and eternal damnation purchaſed, or els the bleſſed &amp; perpetual felicitie is thereby wonne, and the euer during payne of hell is thereby auoyded) wee ought with all carefulnes and diligence to prepare our ſelues for that paſſage, in which the whole concluſion and end of all our doings conſiſteth: becauſe hauing made this paſſage as it requireth &amp; with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooful meanes, wee become happie for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15004:8"/>
euer: whereas contrariwiſe doing euil wee do foreuer loſe the ioyes of para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe. If a iudge were to giue ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in a caſe whereon depended thy whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or yf thow weare to yeeld acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte of ſome adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or office of great importance, thow wouldeſt not fynde repoſe either night or day, thow woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt not ſleep one hower ſoundlie, nor eate one morſel of meat with pleaſing taſte, thow wouldeſt neuer laugh nor vſe any recreation vntil ſuch tyme as thow wert freed from that perillous eſtate and buſineſſe. Alas then, how great is the ignorance of miſerable wordlings, which beeing to make this ſo painful and dangerous a paſſage (wherevpon dependeth all our good) do arryue and come thereunto like vnto brute beaſtes, without any prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration at all.</p>
            <p>When an impriſoned malefactor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath receaued ſentence of death and knoweth hee cannot eſcape, oh how many waylings, and how many lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings maketh the wretche in that time,
<pb facs="tcp:15004:9"/>
ſeeing that aſſuredly he muſt foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with be put to death. In this caſe are all men liuing found to bee, againſt whome as ſoone as euer they be borne, in this miſerable and tranſitorie lyfe, the ſeuere ſentence of death is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced. And ſo do wee all ſtand in this world, as the malefactor ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in priſon, condemned to death &amp; readie to goe vnto execution. Of whome as it is ſaid, that hee lieth in priſon vpon his life, ſo of vs all may it truly bee ſpoken, that wee are in this priſon of the world, and ly vpon our lyues, which beeing conſidered: oh how much ought wee to weep, and how much ought wee to be careful and diligent to prepare our ſelues for death.</p>
            <p>When the marchant had vnderſtood all theſe things, being then brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to great perplexitie, he ſaid vnto the Ermite, o father and maiſter I harte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> deſire that you wil vouchſafe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct mee further in this ſo woorthie and neceſſarie arte, of dying wel, that I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15004:9"/>
may thereby know by this your chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that you haue choſen mee for your ſonne and diſciple: and yf in this moſte healthful ſcience you haue any ſecret or worthie point, I beſeech you for the loue of God before you pas from this our mortal lyf vnto the lyf euerlaſting, to diſcouer vnto mee theſame. Then the Ermite anſwered him, ſaying: my ſonne &amp; welbeloued ſcholler, now do I know that our Lord is hee, that maketh thee to ſpeak, and therefore, I wil not denie thee thy requeſt. Know thow then that I beeing an hundred yeares old, am aſſured that the end of my lyfe cannot but bee neere, wherefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſtudied for the ſpace of ſeauentie yeares, to learne this ſcience of dying wel, It hath pleaſed almightie God to reueal vnto mee ſundry ſecret &amp; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial poynts of theſame, the which I wil co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate and ſhew vnto thee for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> good of all them, that wil learne to dy wel, to the end that by thy meanes they may bee publiſhed vnto the world, and eſpecialy to ſuch godly and deuout
<pb facs="tcp:15004:10"/>
myndes, as aboue all other things deſire to obteyne (through the grace of God) the glorie of paradiſe, yf euer then to any ſacred ſermon thow dideſt giue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiue eare, inſtantly then I pray thee, that vnto this preſent diſcourſe, thow wilt more then euer bee heedful and attentiue, and for the time not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt my ſpeech. And this beeing ſaid the Ermite began his diſcours as follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
            <div type="divisions">
               <head>THE DIVISION OF HIS NARATION.</head>
               <p>THe doctrine of dying wel conteyneth three chapters and twelue golden rules.</p>
               <p>The firſt fowre, in the firſt chapter, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led rules of health, for that whyles wee are in health they teache the meanes to diſpoſe our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues for death.</p>
               <p>The other fowre are called in the ſecond chapter rules of infirmitie, which wee ought to obſerue for dying wel, in our ſicknes.</p>
               <p>The fowre laſt are called in the third chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter rules of extremytie, becauſe wee are by them
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15004:10"/>
inſtructed in fowre principal pointes which wee ought to obſerue at the laſt end of our lyf, to the end to paſſe ſecurely the paſſage of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt chapter ſheweth the long preparation that a man is to make du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the tyme of his health.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond chapter ſheweth the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition more neerer which a man is to make in the tyme of ſicknes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third conteyneth the laſt prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, which a man is to make euen at the very end of his lyf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE FIRST CHAP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER CONTEYNING RVLES</hi> of health, ſheweth what a man ought to do about dying wel; the whyle he is in good health.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt rule.</note> NO man ought to defer vnto the laſt hower, to prepare himſelf to dy, but very behooful it is that euery one diſpoſe himſelf during the whole tyme of his lyf; that wel he may paſſe the laſt paſſage of death. Therefore
<pb facs="tcp:15004:11"/>
then whyleſt thow arte in good health obſerue and keepe theſe fower fruitful rules. The firſt whereof is this, bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes myndful of death, becauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is conteyned a great ſecret which of few is vnderſtood, &amp; of fewer practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for that by the onlie meditation of death in due manner often vſed, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient remedie is found againſt all our ſpiritual infirmities. And therefore Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, Princes, Prelates, and riche men of the worlde, who with all induſtrie do put away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death, do herein greatly offend, becauſe more then any other thing they ought to haue it in continuall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, for that to flie the meditation and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of death is no other thing, then to caſt away from them the grace of the holie ghoſte, which bringeth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the myndes of ſinners, ſuch feareful remembrance, to the end that being thereby terified, they may more eaſelie returne to good lyfe, and attaine to eternal felicitie.</p>
               <p>And to the end that this ſo good and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15004:11"/>
profitable doctrine, may alwayes reſt fixed in thy mynd, I wil in few wordes declare vnto thee, the marueylous frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes that proceed of this continual me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of death.</p>
               <p>The firſt frute that it produceth is a profound and entyre humilitie:<note place="margin">The firſt fruit of the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death.</note> for yf thow think often tymes on death, thow doeſt abaſe and put downe as it were perforce, all pryde arrogancie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolencie, &amp; become gentle humble and meek. For who is hee, that conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in how ſhort a tyme hee is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to aſhes can wax proud? we read in bookes of natural philoſophy that the peacock (a moſte faire bird) behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the great beautie of his gliſtering fethers; he reioyſeth greatly, ſpreading out his maruelous faire taile in ſigne of his gladnes: but eft-ſoones beholding thee foulenes of his feet, he then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh altogether heauie &amp; his pryde is abated, &amp; ſodainlie hee layeth downe his winges and tayle, and for great ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, maketh a lamentable crie. Euen ſo a man made proud either through
<pb facs="tcp:15004:12"/>
his riches, beautie of his bodie, or by glorying in his parentage, or for other worldly cauſes exalted, yf hee ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the miſerie of his end, and in how ſhort a tyme all his glorie is to be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into ſmoke, he wilbe conſtrayned to lay a ſide all pride of mynde, and to cloath himſelfe with humilitie and lowlines.</p>
               <p>To this end at the triumphant coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Pope a woorthy cuſtome is obſerued, that a litle towe beeing tyed to the end of a ſtaf it is held vp and ſet on fyre, and beeing in ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> view ſuddeynlie burnt, one with a loud voice crieth out ſaying. <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi Pater ſancte,</hi> that is to ſay: Euen thus (o holy Father) paſſeth a way the glorie of the world, And for this cauſe alſo a holy Patriarke deſyrous in that high dignitie to keep himſelfe humble and lowlie, ordeyned, that the makers of his tombe (the worke where of he would ſhould continew all the time of his lyfe) euerie time that he was in any great pompe ſhould appeare before him and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15004:12"/>
tel him how his tombe was ſtil in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and that therefore he ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelf for death: and this he did that ſuch remembrance might alwayes in the middeſt of wordlie honour keep him humble and lowlie.</p>
               <p>The other merueylous profit that cometh of the meditation of death,<note place="margin">The ſecond fruit.</note> is a ſuffic e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t remedie againſt coueteouſnes: for the man that perſwadeth himſelf to liue euer in this world, can neuer be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent nor ſatisfied with heaping vp of riches, but becometh wholy inſatiable: yet when hee reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth that ere it be long he muſt leaue all things, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not carie away with him ſo much as one half peny, then beginneth he to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſe all the goodes of the world: This is it which S. Ierome wryteth to Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, ſaying:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 101.</note> 
                  <hi>Facile contemnit omnia, qui ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cogitat ſe eſſe morituru,</hi> that is: he which euer hath in mynde that he ſhal dy, doth eaſelie contemne all things. And Salomon ſaith that a man liuing long in aboundance and glorie of the world,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 12</note> ought to remember the darke and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure
<pb facs="tcp:15004:13"/>
time of death, which beeing once come, ſhal make euerie man know, how vaine and britle haue bene the thinges which are paſt and gon. And Plato highlie commending this medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of death, ſayeth, more worthie phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy then this can not bee found. Whoſo then deſireth in ſhort time, and with eaſe to become a perfect philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, yea a godlie man and beloued of God, let him giue himſelfe wholie to thee meditation of death, and he ſhal fynd by ſure experience, that my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are neyther falſe nor vaine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third fruite. Lib. 16. moral. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t.</note>The third fruit of the remembrance of death is, that all deſire of carnal luſt is theirby eaſely extinguiſhed. S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie witneſſeth this, where hee ſaith: Nothing auayleth ſo much to tame the deſires of the fleſh, then the memorie of death, and to think what this poor fleſh ſhal become, when the ſoule hath left it.</p>
               <p>The ſainctes which wear by nature cloathed with frayle and wanton fleſh, as wee are, through help of this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15004:13"/>
of the mynd, did eaſelie ouercome all fleſhlie motions, as it is red of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſpeciallie of an Ermite who beeing much aſſaulted with the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the fleſh through an imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that the diuel preſented before him of a yong woman that was dead, on whome in the tyme of her lyf he had bene enamoured, hee digged her dead body ſtincking and ful of wormes out of her graue, and caſting himſelf vpon this carcas licked it with his ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue, and ſmelling the filthy ſauour ſaid to his fleſh, go to now cruel and vnta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med beaſt, take now thy fil of that which thow haſte affected with an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meaſurable and diſſolute loue, and ſo by this meanes hee was freed from this his fleſhly temptation.</p>
               <p>The fourth commoditie riſing of this conſideration is, that not only pride couetouſnes and leacherie are thereby ouercome, but alſo euerie other ſinne may by it bee auoyded, as the ſcripture teſtifieth. <hi>In omnibus operibus tuis, memorare nouiſsima tua, &amp; in aeternum non peccabis.</hi> In
<pb facs="tcp:15004:14"/>
all thy woorkes remember the end, and thow ſhalt neuer ſinne. And to theſame effect a holy Abbot ſaid: <hi>Semper memor eſto exitus tui, &amp; non erit delictu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in anima tua,</hi> that is, remember alwayes thine end, &amp; their ſhal neuer bee ſynne in thy ſoule.</p>
               <p>But what need I to remember thee of the merueylous fruits of the firſt rule, which are almoſt innumerable? by this thow ſhalt eaſely get patience in all thy troubles: for euerie man in trouble is greatlie comforted, when he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that by death all aduerſitie is end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that after death great rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des are prepared for all thoſe that bee truely patient. By this; feare is engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred in the ſoule of a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is the beginning of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of lyf: for who is ſo ſence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, that conſidering wel and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of death, doth not from top to toe tremble and quake: And yf thow wilt ſay vnto mee, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not feare death, then muſt I anſwear thee, that it proceedeth of theſe cauſes, eyther that thow arte not a reaſonable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15004:14"/>
creature, or that thow arte without vnderſtanding, or els that thow art ignorant how to conſider and think on it wel. It is no ſinne to feare death, becauſe this feare is natural, and was in our Sauiour Chriſte, in as much as hee was man, and wee fynde that the wiſe and natural philoſophers had an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of death: but out of doubt, it ſhould bee a moſte grieuous &amp; enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſinne, yf for ſuch feare one ſhould deſyre to continew &amp; alwayes remaine in this miſerable lyfe, yea againſt God almightie his wil and pleaſure. And the feare of death in this manner, is repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in holy ſcriptures. It is good then to feare death when ſuch feare induceth thee to the feare and loue of God: but it is a verie il thing to feare it when thow art therby diſpoſed to gaine-ſay the holy wil of God. I ſpeak to thee of this laudable and profitable feare, and thereto I inuite thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſeeing without it holy men haue not profited in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of chriſtian lyfe: I refuſe and greatly blame, that other vnmeaſured
<pb facs="tcp:15004:15"/>
feare of carnal and wicked men.</p>
               <p>If thow take a cuſtome to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber death in all thyne acts and deeds, thow wilt become ſo timerous to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe almightie God, that thow wilt caſt from thee all ſlouth and ſluggiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and that this is true, is apparant, becauſe yf thow ſhouldeſt think that to morrow thow muſt needs dy, ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deynlie thow wouldeſt bee made wel diſpoſed to all good woorkes. Oh how much almes, how many prayers, how great contrition, and what number of teares ſobbes and ſighes wouldeſt thow make and powre out? Faſting would not bee hard for thee, nor to pardon thine enemies, nor yet to make reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of euil gotten goods. And therefore when thow art tempted with ſlouth, or that wel doing grieueth thee, take this ſpur (of the remembrance of death) and therewith prick thyne aſſe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, driuing him on and ſaying toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with Salomon,<note place="margin">Eccl cap. 9.</note> beſtirre thee to doe good, for thow arte to go out of hand where thow ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not woork any more
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15004:15"/>
for thy profit and commoditie. S. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie ſaith, <hi>valde ſe ſollicitat in bone opere,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S. Greg.</note> 
                  <hi>qui ſemper cogitat de extremo fine</hi>) that is: he maketh himſelf verie diligent in good woorks, that alwayes thinketh on his laſt end. And Seneca not diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greing from this our purpoſe ſaith, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing helpeth ſo much to temperance in all things, as the often thinking vpon death: wheer with thow maieſt direct thy whole lyfe, euen as the gouernour of a ſhip doth direct his veſſel, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to bring it wel home into the hauen, ſetteth himſelf at the ſterne in the end therof, ſo putting thy ſelf by conſideration into the end of thy lyfe, thow ſhalt guide thy ſoule to the hauen of health.</p>
               <p>Set thy ſelf then continually to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the end of thy lyfe, and yf their commeth vpon thee a deſire of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie riches, ſay within thy ſelf: I muſt dy ſhortlie, and I may dy euen this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, it ſtandeth mee vpon therefore to take heed, that for tranſitorie gayne I doe not loſe my ſoule and euerlaſting
<pb facs="tcp:15004:16"/>
bliſſe. If thou bee tempted with am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and worldlie glorie, run imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatlie to the remembrance of death, &amp; ſay to thy deſire: If I am to dy ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and paraduenture to day or to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, what need haue I to think how to make my ſelf great in this world, where I am to abyde ſo litle and ſhort a time? So in euerie other carnal de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, and in euerie other temptation that may come to thee, eyther of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, or of enuie, or of pryd, or of glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonie, alwayes thow ſhalt help thy ſelf with the remembrance of death.</p>
               <p>And their ſhalbe no ſinner ſo great, that with this onlie remedie wel vſed and practiſed, ſhal not be able to leaue ſinne, and to do trew pennance with perſeueration. And note that this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie although it bee profitable to all, yet is it much more profitable to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginners, and to thoſe that be nouices in the way of our Lord, then to others that be wel forward or come to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. Therefore (as a holie father ſaith) for thoſe that haue gotten an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15004:16"/>
in ſinne, and for the beginners in ſpiritual lyfe, the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death is no leſſe neceſſarie and needful then daylie bread vnto the lyfe of the bodie: yea it is wrytten, that without ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance hardlie any one can bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for the ſcripture ſaith:<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.2.</note> without feare no man is iuſtified, which feare is wont to proceed of the remembrance of death. Seeing then that thow kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt ſufficientlie the medecine for all thy ſpiritual infirmities, yf thow do not put it in practiſe vſing it when thow haſte need, the fault ſhalbe thine. And yf thow wilt be a diligent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruer of this vniuerſal remedie, at the laſt end of thy lyfe, that may be trewlie ſayd of the, which a biſhop called Theophilus, ſaid vpon his death bed vnto the abbot Arſenius. Bleſſed art thow Arſenius, which haſte alwayes had before thine eyes this laſt hower of death.</p>
               <p>The Marchant hauing with much attenſion heeded theſe the Ermites woords, and not without great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb facs="tcp:15004:17"/>
receaued thereby the aforeſaid fruites, beeing filled with a kynd of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual ſweetnes, hee ſaid vnto the Ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite: Father, of two thinges I do much meruaile, the firſt is, that ſo few by this ſo eaſie way of the remembrance of death, endeuour themſelues to get ſo many marueylous ſpiritual commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: the ſecond is, how it cometh to paſſe that many think and remember themſelues of their lyues laſt hower, &amp; yet notwithſtanding do not attayne to one of the leaſt of theſe fruits and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueylous commodities.</p>
               <p>To this anſwered the olde Ermite, I ſhal not be able (my ſonne) without tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res to anſwere thee, if I aſſoyle thy propounded queſtions, ſeeing ſo great a multitude of chriſtians to bee damned, which ſo eaſilie might ſaue themſelues, for I am by fraternal charitie conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to this grief and compaſsion of the ignorance and negligence of the world.</p>
               <p>To the firſt then I anſwere, that the world is ſo ful of ſo great ignorances and blyndnes, and the health of ſoules
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15004:17"/>
ſo litle or nothing cared for, that one ducat of gold, or one carnal conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is more eſtemed then a thow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand heauens. The leaſt thought or care, that worldlings haue now adayes, is of their ſaluation. Therefore it is not to bee marueyled at that ſo few be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but it is to bee woundered at, and a thing to make euerie man amaſed, that in a reaſonnable humain creature can raigne ſo great blyndnes and ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le care of a thing of ſo great a weight as his ſaluation. To the ſecond I ſay, the cauſe therof is, that they know not how they ſhould think on death, for their thoughts thereon are ſuperficial and ſhort and not vſed with due mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: and therefore it is no meruayle yf of ſuch cogitation they carie a way lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le or no fruite at all. Few preachers of this tyme haue care to teach, in what manner a man ought fruitfullie to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate and think vpon his death. Some becauſe they neyther think vpon it themſelues, nor take delyte in it, as they that be more ſeculer and wordlie then
<pb facs="tcp:15004:18"/>
holie and religious. Some others diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne to handle a matter ſo baſe, ſaying they be things for women and ſimple folkes, and therefore they goe aloft by the toppes of trees, diſputing high things without fruit, and do not ſee that the principal intent of a preacher ought to bee, to teach the way to ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the which conſiſteth in rooting out of vice and planting of vertue: and to do both the one and the other him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <p>Nothing truely is more apt and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable than the continual remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death, and the meditation therof vſed and practiſed as it ought to be. By this meane all wyſe men haue come to be good Chriſtians. And all Catholyke Doctors with all their learning, haue not found a better way to ſhonne ſinne and follow vertue, then the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of death. Wyſe Salomon, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyne Plato, moral Seneca, yea and all our holy men of tyme paſt, as wel lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as vnlearned, haue of one accord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed &amp; approued this our doctrine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15004:18"/>
of death both with woords and deeds. Onlie the miſerable and ill Chriſtians be thoſe, that make therat a ieaſt, and mock and ſcorne it, but in the end they wil fynde themſelues mocked and deceaued.</p>
               <p>Then ſaid the Marchant, let vs let others go at their peril, that wil not ſeek to bee ſaued, and let vs attend to our owne ſaluation: wherefore with great deſire I look that you vouchſafe to inſtruct mee, in what manner the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death ought to be vſed, that it may bring fourth the fruits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue rehearſed. The Ermite anſwered, yf I yeild to thy deſire, I doubt I ſhalbe to long, yet conſidering that moderate length in a doctrine profitable and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie is not reprehenſible, eſpeciallie when the hearer is wel diſpoſed, it ſhal not be grieuous vnto me in the firſt rule to lengthen my ſpeach more then I thought,<note place="margin">Three mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to haue the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of death vvith profit.</note> for thy greater profit and better contentation. Marke then that by three meanes a man may haue thee remembrance of death, the which ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:15004:19"/>
bring thee to taſte thereof in ſuch wiſe, that exerciſing thy ſelf in them, thow ſhalt reap the fruites before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt meane.</note>The firſt meane is, willinglie to heare ſpeaking and preaching of the terrible conditions &amp; paynes of death, and willinglie to read ſpiritual books, where that matter is ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled, and where the ſtories and examples bee written of many perſons, which by feare of death haue bene conuerted. For ſuch exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples help much, and not a litle moue ſinners to repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond meane.</note>The ſecond meane much more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual then the firſt, is willinglie and oftentimes to go to ſee men when they be in the agonie of death, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they paſſe out of this lyfe, and when they be borne vnto their graues: and beſydes to accuſtome to viſit Churche-yeards and monuments and ſepulchres of the dead.</p>
               <p>Oh how profitable is ſuch an exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe as this, yf it bee vſed with a deep and diſcreet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration: where-vpon
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15004:19"/>
the wiſe man ſaith:<note place="margin">Eccl. cap. 7.</note> it is better to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the howſe of mourning, then to the howſe of feaſting. Wheare the dead bee lamented, there occaſion is geuen vs to remember our ſelues of the end of all men.</p>
               <p>And the better to print this remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in themſelues,<note place="margin">Beholding cauſeth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring.</note> ſome haue taken a dead mannes head, and kept it in a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret place, and certaine tymes in the week ſet it before their eyes, and verie wel and diligentlie conſidered it, and by way of imagination kept long talk with it, and this not euerie day but once or twiſe a week, becauſe it ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, more our affection, then it would do yf euerie day wee ſhould ſee the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame: for by long cuſtome being once made familiar vnto vs, it would moue vs nothing at all.</p>
               <p>A great ſinner that ſome tyme vſed theſame, aſked diuers queſtions of a dead mannes ſkul which he kept, as thus, tel me yf it pleaſe the (o lothſome and deformed head, whoſe head haſte thow bene and what cauſe hath made
<pb facs="tcp:15004:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15004:19"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15004:21"/>
thee ſo vglie? where bee thy fine yealow heares? where is thy faire white fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head? where is thy cleare ſhyning eyes? where is thy tongue that ſo wel could ſpeak? where be all the liuelie ſences of thy bodie? where is thy face ſo goodlie and ſo faire? where is thy trim delicate ſkin and fleſh? Thow arte now without a noſe, without eyes, without eares, thow haſte not ſo much as one haire left vpon thy head: what raſor hath bene ſo cruel that it hath ſhauen away all thy haire and fleſh; euen to the very bone? who hath taken away thy beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? who hath made thee ſo monſtrous and il fauoured? whereof cometh ſo great deformitie? Thow arte to vs that be liuing ſo horrible and vglie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, that thow putteſt euerie one in feare.</p>
               <p>The head with lamenting voyce &amp; wayling woordes he imagined to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him thus, I was the head of a young man, beautyful, rich and mightie, which in the ſhort tyme of my flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing youth gaue my ſelfe wholie to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15004:21"/>
luſt and wordlie pleaſures. I took no heed of my fathers admonitions, godlie talk I vtterlie diſpiſed, mocking ſimple and deuout people: and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing that I ſhould haue bene a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tyme happie in the world, I neuer thought vpon death. I was altogether drowned in worldlie deſires, and ſo liuing in io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, ſinging, dauncing and laughing, I was ſudainly aſſaulted, with a ſudain &amp; deadlie diſeaſe, in which ſeeing my ſelf in ſo ſhort a tyme depriued of all my ioy, and in a manner deſperate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I had neuer done good workes, I began with my ſelf not without ſore grones and deep ſighes to conſider myne eſtate, ſaying: alas vnhappie that I am, I ſee my ſelfe depriued of all thinges that did delight mee: o poor yongman whereto am I now brought? I muſt leaue the world that I did loue ſo much: alas what helpeth me now my vading goodlie beautie, in this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate? o cruel death, how bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the remembrance of thee to a merie harte, which hath alwayes flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed
<pb facs="tcp:15004:22"/>
in delightful pleaſures? o how horrible is thy preſence to a young man healthful, luſtie and beauteful, &amp; to him that taketh delight onelie in worldlie pleaſures and proſperities: I ſee thow comeſt to mee lyke a traytor, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceytes, laying wayt for my lyf, I feel thow byndeſt mee hand and foot, and by thy cruel forces ſuddaynlie bound and taken, I ſee I am drawne as a thief, and malefactor to the miſerable puniſhment of myne end: ſeeking ayd in ſo great ſorrow and payne I finde no help nor ſuccour, neyther of riches, nor of freinds, nor yet of kynsfolkes, &amp; why? the hower appoynted of God is comme, I muſt needs go, and I know not whether, I depart from this world that I loue ſo wel, I leaue all my world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie goodes, and my worldlie felicitie greatly againſt my wil: and ſo weeping and howling without hope of Gods help, I was of cruel death preuented and in a moment loſt all my proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the wreched ſoule was aſsigned to the euerlaſting paynes of hel, and my
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15004:22"/>
corruptible bodie loſt all his beautie, and became loth ſome and ſtinking, &amp; the food of wormes.</p>
               <p>This ſinner with this head made many other long diſcourſes, and had many imagined ſpeaches, ful of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction and verie profitable to him that deſireth to dy wel, the which did in ſuch wiſe imprint in his mynd the remembrance of death, as thereby hee profited greatly in the way of ſaluation, for he thought, that all the miſeries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned hee might proue in himſelf, yf hee ſhould not againſt the hower of death be wel prepared.</p>
               <p>But to be ſhort, I leaue this ſecond mean, and come to the third, the which is yet of much more effect, then eyther the firſt or the ſecond. The reaſon whereof may eaſilie be comprehended, for in the firſt the miſerable paines and anguiſhes of death are heard with the eares, in the ſecond they be as it weer ſeene with the eyes, but in the third wee feel them in our ſelues. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſurely doth moue much, the ſeeing
<pb facs="tcp:15004:23"/>
doth yet moue more, but the feeling farre more moueth then either of the other. Yf then the firſt and ſecond mean to meditate vpon death do not moue thee, take the third; which is practiſed in this manner, Imagine with all the forces of thy mynd, that thow art preſentlie in that laſt ſicknes, in which thow ſhalt be compelled to paſſe from this lyfe to another, and thow ſhalt transforme into thee all thoſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents, which in that hower may hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen thee, and make them with thy mynde preſent vnto thee, intentiuelie conſidering all the anguiſhes, ſorro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes and paynes of that heauie &amp; dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful tyme, as though now preſentlie thow weareſt in the verie agonie of death, and think thereon not as it ſhal come, but as yf euen now at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant thow dideſt feel in thy ſelf the verie paynes and agonie thereof: with thy thought then and with thyne ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, thow ſhalt ſuppoſe that thow art in thy bed, forſaken of the phiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as one without all hope of recouering
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15004:23"/>
bodilie health, when thy to<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gue fayleth thee, the ſences of thy bodie ceaſe to do their woonted offices, thow ſeeiſt no more, nor more ſhal euer ſee in this lyfe, thow ſpeakeſt not, nor euer ſhalt in this world ſpeak more, eyther wel or il, thow heareſt no more, thow ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt no more, thy pulſe is ſcarſelie to be perceyued, thy bodie in all partes vexed with payne forſaketh thee, thy mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers moue no more, thow lieſt in thy bed like an image of wood or ſtone, thow ſweateſt from top to toe for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream payne and torment, their doth remaine in thee but a litle breath, and in this manner, ſorrowing, gaping, for breath and ſtriuing with death, thow lyeſt for a litle tyme in ſuch horrible &amp; terrible paynes, both of mynde and of bodie, as in this lyfe thow neuer dideſt feel ſo bitter griefes, The ſynful ſoule ſeing herſelf forſaken and abandoned of the bodie, whome ſhe loued ſo deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, with deep ſighes (her eſtate tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowlie weyghed) knoweth ſhe can haue neyther ſuccour nor help of the world
<pb facs="tcp:15004:24"/>
in this her extream need: and therfore on her owne part willing to comfort and helpe her ſelf, beginneth to think on her workes, yf yet in them ſhe might finde ſome refuge: but not able to finde in her ſelf any other workes then weightie and wicked vices, ſhe maketh far greater ſorrow then before. Yet ſearching yf on any ſyde ſhe might finde refreſhing in this her hard and bitter caſe, ſhe then with wayling tourneth her to the mercie of God, but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal knowing this her conuerſion to riſe of ſeruile feare ſeeith her ſelf not in this laſt hower woorthie of mercie, but rather of all rigour of iuſtice, foorth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with is wholy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded, not knowing how to eſcape this horrible and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful iudgement of the moſte great &amp; iuſt iudge, before whome the poore and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſoule is now to bee called to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peere in iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; to render a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral accompt of all her actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the leaſt thought; then the ſorrowfull ſoule ſeeing her ſelf in ſo great extremitie, and not able to ſatisfie ſo great a iudge:
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15004:24"/>
becauſe ſo ſtrait an accompt is demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of her, as of all her worldlie goods, of her worldlie honours, of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of her bodie, and of their powers, and how ſhe hath vſed them to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of her creatour, and the miſerable ſoule not knowing what to anſweare, the eyes of her vnderſtanding beeing opened, ſhe knoweth that ſhe is not of her ſelf by the giltineſſe of her owne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce woorthie of glorie but deſerueth payne, and therefore vtterly deſperate, ſeeing ſhe can fynde no relief to eaſe her vnſhunnable payn, but rather the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, therof ſeeing the diuels appeare before her with moſte ſoule and vglie ſhapes, like fiers lyons watching to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour her, ſhe then more vnhappie than any other creature, in that inſtant feeleth ſuch bitter grief and ſorrow, that ſhe is forced for vehemencie of her vnſpeakable paſsions, to forſake for euer her miſerable and contemptible bodie. And ſo ſuddaynlie taken by thoſe cruel fiendes of hel, ſhe is with ſuch grief as cannot bee vttered bound and
<pb facs="tcp:15004:25"/>
brought againſt her wil, to that vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie and ſorrowful countrie, where beeing caſt in burning fire ſhe their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth in euerlaſting wo and payne: and the dead carkas now become car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion, and all foule and ſtinking, with a litle ſound of belles, and with weeping teares of kinsfolkes is brought vnto the graue, whereafter it is put in the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, it is ſoone deuoured of wormes, &amp; tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into earth and aſhes. And then is verified, the ſaying of Dauid in the Pſalme,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Perijt memoria eius cum ſonitu, &amp; iuſtus in eternum permanet,</hi> that is: his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie hath periſhed with the ſound, &amp; the iuſt abydeth for euer, and thus is the end of this worldes pomp and glorie.</p>
               <p>Of how great effect the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death may bee, is ſhewed by many examples, and chiefly by that which Iohn Climacus recyteth of a moſte negligent and keycold religious man, who taken with a grieuous ſicknes, was within a while rapt in ſpirit, and when his ſoule was (as it weer) cleane ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15004:25"/>
from the bodie, hee ſaw the iuſt iudgments of God, &amp; afterward beeing returned to himſelf, by &amp; by he deſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched away all thoſe that then wear with him in his ſel, and their ſhut him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf vp, and liued with bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter xij. yeares, neuer ſpeaking to any perſon ſo much as one woord, vntil hee was neer vnto death, that then the other monkes deſirous to receaue, of him ſome good inſtructions did break open his chamber door and entred in vnto him, and prayed him that it might not bee grieuous vnto him, in this his laſt hower, to ſpeak in the way of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, for the edification of others, and diſcloſe vnto them in what manner ſo ſudaynlie from ſo great negligence, hee was come to ſo great perfection, who after much intreatie, made them this anſwere: pardon mee yf I do not vſe many words, and aſſure your ſelues, none can euer ſinne grieuouſly which haue the true feeling of the reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of death. The monkes buried him with great deuotion, but the next day
<pb facs="tcp:15004:26"/>
following, when his bones were ſought by ſuch as deſired to reuerence them, they wear not found. Whereby they knew how much the feeling in deed of the remembrance of death doth pleaſe God, and what effect it woorketh, and how expedient it is for them that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to become good: ſince that in one moment it can make euen thoſe that bee verie negligent, zealouſly diſpoſed and moſt feruent to euerie good woork. And now ſeeing that with more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixitie then I ment I haue handled this firſt rule, the more to ſhew the vtilitie thereof, the ſhorter wil I now enforce my ſelf to be in the rules following.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond rule.</note> THE ſecond principal rule of the arte to dy wel conſiſteth in diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeing of a mannes laſt wil and teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for a wyſe man ought not to dy without making his teſtament. And although hee bee willing to make it, yet ought hee not to deferre it to the laſt extremitie. Therefore ſaid Iacob to Laban,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtum eſt, vt aliquando domut meae
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15004:26"/>
diſponam,</hi> that is to ſay: It is meet, that without any more adoe I diſpoſe of my howſe. And Eſay ſaid to Ezechias king of Iudea: <hi>Diſpone domut tuae, quia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Regum 20.</note> 
                  <hi>morieris &amp; no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viues,</hi> that is: ſet thy howſe in order, for thow ſhalt die, and not liue. Hee that at the beginning of his ſicknes maketh his teſtament, may the better prouyde for himſelf and his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, becauſe he taketh the fitter opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie to do it with greater foreſight and iudgement, and is more readdie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward at the point of death to attend to the health of his ſoule.</p>
               <p>The diuel doth his endeuour to make thee defer the making of thy teſtament, to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that after when thow ſhalt be grieued with thy ſicknes, thow mayeſt alſo be troubled with thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and kinred, who all ſeek their owne commoditie and litle care for thy ſoules health. Therefore yf thow bee wyſe, thow wilt make thy teſtament ſo ſoone as thow canſt: and to the end thow mayeſt make it as it beheueth &amp; with the more commoditie I wil teach
<pb facs="tcp:15004:27"/>
thee certaine ſecrets concerning the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame.</p>
               <p>Firſt then I muſt put thee in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that thow do not to much truſte vnto freindes or kinsfolkes, when they promiſſe thee to do good for thy ſoule after thy death, for yf in thy lyf tyme thow wilt bee negligent to procure help and neceſſary prayers for thy ſelf, far more negligent wil they bee when thow arte gone. This is ſo playnlie ſeene euerie day by manifeſt experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, that it would ſeeme a thing vtterly needles to go about to proue it.</p>
               <p>Secondlie I am to aduertiſe thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that thow ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not make any legacies which can bee more profitable for thy ſoule, then legacies to haue maſſes ſayd for thee, the which is proued by all the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, &amp; chiefly by Gabriel Beele vpon the canon of the Maſſe, and by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Doctor S. Thomas Aquinas vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fourth of the ſentences. Who af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Maſſe to bee alwayes auayle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the ſoules that are in purgatorie, yea although the prieſt which ſaid it
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15004:27"/>
were in deadlie ſinne, becauſe he as the miniſter; ſayeth it in the perſon of the Churche militant, which is euer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie I aduiſe thee, that thow or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne and appoynt thy legacies in ſuch wyſe, as without delay after thow be dead, they may bee performed and thy wil executed, aſwel for the maſſes, as for the almes which thow ſhalt leaue to be beſtowed. For (as Iohn Gerſon ſayth) far better it is to haue them ſaid out of hand, then to tarie diuers yeares, becauſe the ſooner they be ſaid, the ſooner the ſoules be deliuered out of the paynes of purgatorie.</p>
               <p>Fourthlie I muſt put thee in mynde to confeſſe thy ſelf, and to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate before thow make thy teſtament. For when thereby thow art the more in the fauour of God, legacies of almes &amp; maſſes do far more auaile thee, then yf thow weert out of the ſtate of grace. This is grounded vpon the doctrine of S. Thomas in the fourth of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, where hee ſaith, the ſatisfaction
<pb facs="tcp:15004:28"/>
inioyned of the confeſſor made when thow art in deadly ſinne doth not take away the payne of the ſinne remitted: although the opinion of Scotus, which holdeth the contrarie, bee more fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, but yet in our caſe I iudge that of S. Thomas to be the more ſure.</p>
               <p>Laſtly there is come to my mynde an other thing to remember thee of, which I heard of that noble capitaine Bartholomew of Bergamo, which is, that yf thow wilt make a ſingular good teſtament and a perfect preparation, to dy wel; then beare thy ſelf alwayes in ſuch ſorte whileſt thow art a liue, and let thy wordes bee ſo charitable direct and cleere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning thy laſt wil in thy lyfe tyme, that after thy death no man may haue iuſt cauſe to complayne of thee. Yf thow arte a ſecular man in thus doing thow maiſt leaue thy heyres in peace without ſtryf, which is the beſt inheritance that thow maiſt leaue vnto them, &amp; moreouer thow doeſt therein the better prouyde for thy ſaluation &amp; theirs, and therefore thow oughteſt in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15004:28"/>
any caſe to obſerue this good &amp; profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble leſso<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the making of thy teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <p>But yf thow bee a ſpiritual man not hauing worldlie goods to diſtribute, thow mayeſt make a ſpiritual teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, after the example of many ſainctes, which haue ſpoken in their teſtaments not of wordlie wealth &amp; earthlie poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsions, but of ſpiritual and heauenly thinges.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The thir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rule.</note> THE third rule of the arte to dy wel, which is to bee practiſed in health, is daylie prayer, to obtayne at Gods ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des a good and laudable death. For as without God his grace no man ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do any good or meritorious woork, nor think my good thought ſo a good death without his grace wee can in no wyſe look for. Therefore wee ought euerie day to pray vnto God, that he wil for his infinite goodnes graunt vs a good and happie end. In obſeruing the cuſtome ſo to pray, S. Auguſtine, and S. Catherine of Siena were wont to ſay this verſe of the Pſalme, which is verie
<pb facs="tcp:15004:29"/>
fit for the purpoſe. <hi>Illumina oculos meos, ne vnquam obdormiam in morte ne quando di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat inimicus meus, praeualui aduerſus eum.</hi> That is, lighten myne eyes that I ſleep not in death, leaſt that at any tyme my enemy ſay I haue preuailed againſt him. And yf thow canſt ſay none other, at leaſt thow ſhalt ſay a <hi>Pater noſter</hi> and <hi>Aue Maria</hi> deuoutly euerie day; with this inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that God wil geue thee grace to dy lyke a true chriſtian. And although it be a thing very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for the obtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſuch ſingular grace to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the glorious mother of God, as alſo to the apoſtles, martirs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſors, virgins &amp; other ſaintes in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe thow oughteſt particularly to inuocate the ayd of thy good angel, who for ſo much as hee hath a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar care ouer thee, wil not faile in that ſo dangerous and perillous an howre to aſsiſt thee with a ſinguler and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial help. Some bee accuſtomed to ſay this prayer. <hi>O Domine Ieſu Chriſte depre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r te propter illam amaritudinem, quàm pro me miſero peccatore ſuſtinuiſti in cruce, maxime
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15004:29"/>
quando nobiliſsima anima tua egreſſa eſt de corpore tuo, miſerere animae meae in egreſſu ſuo, Amen.</hi> That is: O Lord Ieſu Chriſte, I beſeech thee for that bitternes, which for mee wretched ſinner thow didſt endure on the croſſe, eſpetialy when thy moſte noble ſoule went foorth of thy body, haue mercy vpon my ſoule when it ſhal departe out of my body. A chanon reguler of the order of S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtyne, after his death appearing to a freind of his, told him, that by meanes of this prayer, which hee had ordinarily in his lyfe tyme ſaid euery day, there was graunted vnto him a verie good happie and quiet death. Yf thow ſhalt then daylie vſe ſo to recommend thy ſelf to God, to the ſaincts and angels, thow mayeſt hope neuer to be abando<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of them in that caſe. And although in time of peſtilence or of war, thow fynde thy ſelf depriued of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes help, do not doubt: For in that hower thy good angel and the ſaincts wil not fayle of their deſired helpe in
<pb facs="tcp:15004:30"/>
due tyme, as it is knowne to haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to many that truſted in their ayd.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth and laſt rule.</note> THE fourth rule, which ought to be obſerued in health is called mortification. The deuout men that haue treated of this doctrine, wryte, that a man ought euerie day to dy, that is to ſay, to mortifie his proper paſsions &amp; ſences, as for example, one doth abuſe thee in wordes, thy paſsion would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him, and thow wouldeſt not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to tread thee (as it weer) vnder his feet, but thereby thow ſhouldeſt ſhew thy ſelf not to haue mortifyed thy affections, whereas holding thy peace and mortifiyng that violent motion, thow ſhouldeſt ſhew thy ſelfe to bee dead to the world, and that thy reaſon comaundeth ouer thy inferiour affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p>When thyne eye would ſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a beautiful creature, yf thow re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine thy deſire, thow ſhalt mortifie
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15004:30"/>
it, but yf thow ſuffer thy ſelf to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away by ſenſualitie, then ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt thow not be called dead vnto the world but aliue. Therefore it is ſaid of holy men, that yf thow deſire to dy a trew chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and at the end of thy lyfe to enioy euerlaſting bliſſe, it behoueth thee euerie day whileſt thow liueſt many times to dy. And thus oftentymes dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpiritually, thow ſhalt learne the arte to dy wel, and ſafelie and without feare come to the end of thy lyfe, with good preparation, and their ſhalbe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in thee the ſaying of bleſſed S. Gregorie the great, when hee ſaid: <hi>Non timebit facere, quod ſe nouerit bene didiciſſe,</hi> that is to ſay: hee ſhal not feare to doe that, which hee knoweth himſelf to haue learned wel to do.</p>
               <p>And thus haſte thow ſomwhat vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, how thow oughteſt to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare thy ſelf for death in tyme of health, which is practiſed beforehand, and in it conſiſteth fowre rules or prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal points, the firſt is called the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of death, the ſecond, the
<pb facs="tcp:15004:31"/>
making of thy teſtament: the third prayer: the fourth, mortification.</p>
               <p>And now come wee to the ſecond parte where wee ſhal ſpeak more briefly of the preparation a man ought to make; when hee beginneth to bee ſick, and it conteyneth fowre other principal rules.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>THE SECOND CHAPTER</hi> wherein is principally treated of the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration which a man ought to make in the begining of ſicknes, and conteyneth fowre principal rules.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt rule.</note> THE firſt rule is, that when thow feeleſt thy ſelfe depriued of health, thow do think by and by, that almightie God, who is the chief goodnes, is hee that ſendeth thee this ſicknes for the greater weal of thy ſoule, and to the end that thow ſhouldeſt leaue thy euil lyf: or els yf alreadie thow haeſt amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thy euil lyfe, that then thow mayeſt bee preſerued in good lyfe with greater perfection. The wyſeman ſayd: <hi>Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitas
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:15004:31"/>
grauis ſobriam facit animam,</hi> that is to ſay: A grieuous ſicknes maketh the ſoule ſober. And Dauid ſaith: <hi>Multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſunt infirmitates eorum, poſtea accelera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt:</hi> that is, Their infirmities weare multiplied, and afterward they made haſte: Therefore this ſicknes without doubt being ſent thee of God for thy profit, thow ougheſt to receyue with great patience, and thank him for his giftes. For although theſe ſtrypes and fatherlie corrections afflict and greeue the bodie, yet they cure the ſoule: and of this thy prayſe-woorthie patience, many good fruites ſhal follow. Firſt thow ſhalt greatly merit in the ſight of God, being conformable to his iuſt and holie wil and pleaſure, and it ſhalbe a ſatisfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy ſinnes: and the more, in that thow ſhalt the more eaſilie ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſicknes it ſelf, and ſo yf God wil that thow ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, thow ſhalt ſooner bee deliuered. Whereas on the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie part, yf thow ſhouldeſt bee impatie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thow ſhouldeſt ſynne, and thy ſicknes ſhould bee prolonged, and peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb facs="tcp:15004:32"/>
alſo encreaſed: and thow weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by thyne impatience, ſhouldeſt then with more difficultie beare euerie litle payne or grief. To this purpoſe S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine ſaid: <hi>Si Deum diligis quod faecit Deus diligis,</hi> that is: Yf thow loue God, thow loueſt that which God doeth.</p>
               <p>And S. Hierome ſaith, <hi>Qui cum dolore agritudinem ſuſcipit, ſignum eſt quod Deum non ſufficienter diligit,</hi> that is to ſay: It is a ſigne hee doth not loue God with all his hart as hee ought to do, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth ſicknes with greef of mynde.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond rule.</note> THE ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d rule of preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that ought to be made in ſicknes is, ſo ſoone as thow perceyueſt thy ſelf to bee ſick, that thow think thow mayeſt dy of this diſeaſe, and that thow therefore doe diſpoſe thy ſelfe to receyue the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments of holy Churche, as yf thow wert ſure thow ſhouldeſt then dy in deed. In this caſe the deuil is wont to lay many ſtoppes to let a man to doe ſo great good. Firſt hee putteth in his mynde that hee ſhal not dy of that ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15004:32"/>
and that their is no peril at all. After that hee procureth the phiſition to giue him too much hope of lyfe, and lykewyſe all them of the howſe. And his fteindes and kinsfolkes to comforte him, ſaying, Sir bee of good cheere, for ye ſhal amend verie ſhortlie. And yf any religious man come to viſit him, they warne him or tel him, that for nothing in the world he put any feare in him, or tel him that hee is in peril to dy. All theſe bee woorkings of our ghoſtelie enemie. Therefore a wyſeman ſo ſoone as hee feeleth himſelf ſick, ſaith, I wil confeſſe my ſelf and receyue the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſacrament, and prepare my ſelf for death, and after let God woork his holy wil of mee as it pleaſeth him, for that I am his creature.</p>
               <p>But note that when hee hath made this good determination, the deuil doth not yet ceaſſe to make him delay ſo good a deed, and beginneth to moue his wyf (yf hee bee maried) and his kinsfolkes to leaue them ſome of his worldlie ſubſtance, and they talk to
<pb facs="tcp:15004:33"/>
him of many hard thinges, and all worldlie. In the meane while the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes encteaſeth and the ſickman ſaith diſpatche theſe buſineſſes, I wil in any wyſe bee confeſſed. In ſuche caſe I would aduyſe thee to haue an eye to the principal, which is the health of thy ſoule, for the malice of the deuil layeth many ſnares to catche thee. Say not I wil firſt diſpatche my worldlie buſines and then confeſſe mee, becauſe it is the deuil that maketh thee to ſpeak ſo: but ſay I wil firſt confeſſe me and prepare for my ſoule, and after I wil diſpoſe theſe other things of the world, becauſe this buſines of the ſoule doth (to ſay the truth) importe mee much more then a thowſand worldes. And doubt not when thow ſhalt be confeſſed thow ſhalt haue in thee the grace of God, and bee better able then; to diſpoſe of thy worldlie things with more iudgement and better meanes.</p>
               <p>Now marke wel my ſonne, for in this rule I wil diſcouer vnto thee ſome goodlie ſecretes, which commonlie are
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15004:33"/>
not ſet fourth of ſome deuout men which haue entreated of this arte to dy wel. All how ſhold and worldlie care beeing then ſet a ſide, I wil haue thee after thow haſte examined thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to make thy confeſsion to a good and learned prieſt, following the example of S. Auguſtine, who in his laſt ſicknes, would haue none to enter into his chamber for ſome dayes together vntil he had made a diligent ſearch, &amp; examination of his conſcience. And ſo hee had written before to a nephew of his, and perſwaded him, that putting a ſyde all earthlie care in his ſicknes, hee ſhould turne himſelfe wholie to God almightie, with great contrition: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the bleſſed woundes of our moſte mercyful redeemer, and beway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling &amp; deteſting al his faultes paſt. In this tyme, it ſhould be verie good to ſay the ſeaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> penite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tial Pſalmes, as did theſame S. Auguſtyne, who turning his heauie &amp; pale face to the wall where the ſeauen Pſalmes weere written, and beeing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all other care ſequeſtred, ſayd them
<pb facs="tcp:15004:34"/>
with great aboundance of teares, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding of almightie God mercie &amp; pardon for his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>And after ſuch a contrition and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance for thy ſinnes thow ſhalt then make thy confeſsion with an exact exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of thy conſcience, and after while thow art in perfect memorie thow ſhalt receyue the bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is called in latyn <hi>viaticum,</hi> that is to ſay: a viage prouiſion, becauſe it is neceſſarie and needful in the way by which wee haue to paſſe from this lyf to the next. With how great reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and deuotion ſo great a ſacrament is to be receyued I wil not (for breui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſake) heere declare, but wil referre thee for this matter to the examples of the ſainctes, and eſpecially for the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage out of this lyfe to the glorious doctor S. Hierome, where thow ſhalt fynde with how many teares, and with how merueylous great conſideration hee receyued the bleſſed ſacrament, all which is wrytten for our example.</p>
               <p>When now thow ſhalt be commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15004:34"/>
immediatelie thow ſhalt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire; that growing woors, thow mayeſt haue the ſacrament of extreme vnction, when it ſhal ſeeme good to thy ghoſtly father. And heer I wil tel thee, a good note, which is that yf thow take the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of extreme vnctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſuch manner, as I haue inſtructed thee, and yf thow pray to our Lord aſwel as thow canſt, and oftentymes repeat thy prayer, and perſeuer in deſire vntil death, aſking of God, that for his infinite mercy, and by the vertue of this holie Sacrament of extreme vnction, he wil graunt thee plenarie remiſsion in this lyfe of all thy ſinnes, that is to ſay, that when thy ſoule ſhalbe ſeperated from thy bodie, immidiatly without touche of the paynes of purgatorie, thow mayeſt flie to the bliſſe of euerlaſting lyfe: Iohn Gerſon Chancelor of Paris, and William Altiſsiodorenſis affirme (with whome agreeth alſo Peter de Palude) that in this caſe the ſick dying with the diſpoſition and holy prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before mentioned, ſhal not feel the
<pb facs="tcp:15004:35"/>
paynes of purgatorie, but ſtraight way ſhal aſcend to the eternal ioyes of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. And it ſeemeth Caſsiobrus was of this opinion touching the plenary remiſsion in alleaging this verſe,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſalm. 115.</note> 
                  <hi>Diru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſti Domine vincula mea, tibi ſacrificabo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiam laudis,</hi> that is: thow haſte broken my bandes in ſonder o lord, to thee wil I yeeld the ſacrifice of prayſe, which (as ſome hold opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) being ſayd in the end of a mannes lyf doth procure that his ſinnes be remitted, that is, as I expound it, touching the payne: for as for the fault; perfect contrition ſufficeth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold my welbeloued ſonne how eaſilie a chriſtian may obtayne plenarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion and ful pardon of his ſinnes. See beſydes how much it importeth to knowe this arte of dying wel, and how greatlie it profiteth how to knowe to make preparation, with the ſacraments of holy Churche. And yf thow weart at that point that thow couldeſt then not haue the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, in this caſe thy good deſire with the continewance of the ſaid prayer would ſuffice thee: And ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15004:35"/>
by the opinion of Iohn Gerſon a verie Catholike doctor, &amp; William Altiſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorenſis thow ſhouldeſt lykewyſe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne plenarie remiſsion by the vertue of that prayer. Yea without the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments actuallie receyued. Therefore marke this notable ſaying, and keep it in memorie, and prayſe the infinite goodnes of God, who for ſo ſhort and few wordes, doth deliuer vs from the payne of ſo great a fyer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third rule.</note> THE third rule for the tyme of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is, that thow prepare thy ſelf to be conſtant and ſtrong againſt the ſundrie temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whear with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil wil trouble thee. Wherefore it is to be known, according to the doctrine of diuynes, that the deuil is more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in tempting at the tyme of death, then in the tyme of health: for he thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the diſeaſe to be mortal; ſaith to himſelf, yf I loſe this ſoule at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, I loſe it for euer, wherfore I wil not leaue to doe what I can to winne it. And ſo calling to him a multitude
<pb facs="tcp:15004:36"/>
of deuils in diuers manners they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his damnation, laying wait euen vntil the end of his paſſage. Firſt they temp him with impatience whervnto for ſorrow and payne hee is much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined. When they cannot ouercome this way they take an other and tempt him with his owne, pleaſing of himſelf and his proper reputation, deſirous to perſwade him that hee is one of great perfection, and conſtant in his aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and that hee hath done many good woorkes woorthy of great reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence, &amp; with this temptation deuout men are ſpeciallie vexed, and this temptation is much to be feared, becauſe many haue bene brought in peril by it, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny damned. Wherefore it behoueth them to haue recourſe to humilitie, and to conſider our owne faultes which in deed be many, and to acknowledge the mercie and goodnes of our Sauiour, from whome all goodnes proceedeth without any proper merit or deſeruing of ours, more ouer by diuers wayes and meanes they endeuour themſelues to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15004:36"/>
make him think, that hee ſhal not dy of this infirmitie, and this they do to the end hee go not about to prepare and fortifie himſelf againſt them, and that they may take him at vnawares.</p>
               <p>But yf thow wilt bee wyſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, thow ſhalt prepare thy ſelfe in euerie leaſt ſicknes, as yf thow weart out of all doubt thow ſhouldeſt dy of that diſeaſe. And yf they ſee they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deceyue thee this way, then they ſet hand to greater blowes, and with falſe arguments beginne to cal thee back from the truthe of the chriſtian faith. In this caſe yf thow be not verie warie, thow art like to bee catched in their nettes: therefore I giue thee war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that thow giue not eare to their deceitful arguing, nor diſpute with them in any wyſe, becauſe ſo, thow ſhouldeſt bee ſodeynlie bound and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The beſt remedie in this ſtraight wil bee, with tongue &amp; hart to ſay the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of our faith, that is the Creed, &amp; to confeſſe thow beleeueſt all that our holie mother the Catholyke Churche
<pb facs="tcp:15004:37"/>
beleeueth, and ſo cauſe the goſpels to be red vnto thee, with this temptation the learned are more troubled then the vnlearned, therefore it is good to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our vnderſtanding vnto obedience of faith, and not to ſearch out the truthe therof by reaſon, but with humilitie to referre our ſelues to the iudgement of our fore-fathers and the Catholyke Churche. Yf in this temptation of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelitie thow ſhalt make due reſiſtance, then with their laſt battayle they wil tempt thee with deſparation, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thee that in this lyfe thow haſte not vſed thy ſelfe in ſuch wyſe as thow deſerueſt to be ſaued: and to put thee beſyde all hope they wil bring to thy memorie all thy defects and wants, and tel thee thy confeſsions haue not bene good, nor thy communications merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and that thow haſt not done eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing for the loue of God, but for feare of hel and for thyne owne profit. Then it wilbe tyme to runne to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite mercie of our louing and ſweet lord God, and remember thy ſelf that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15004:37"/>
his ſonne for our ſaluation did become man, and as man ſuffered hunger, and thirſt, paynes, and torments, and finallie vpon the croſſe for our ſaluation, an opprobrious and ſhameful death. Thow ſhalt anſwere then to the enemie: it is true, thow doeſt not deſerue paradiſe, nor diddeſt woork in all thy lyfe by which thow couldeſt merit ſo great bliſſe, but thy merciful lord is hee, that of his infinite mercie and goodnes hath merited for thee; and purchaſed thee paradiſe, when hee died on the croſſe for thy redemption. Yf thow ſay this, they ſhal remayne confounded like hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh beaſtes, not knowing what more to do againſt thy ſaluation: except (God permitting it) they appeare vnto thee in verie horrible and feareful ſhapes, to geue thee ſome payne and to make thee afeard, to the intent they may more eaſilie take thee in their malitious trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, whyleſt thy mynde is occupied with ſuch trouble, and greef. But yf thow wilt runne for refuge to the help of our bleſſed Ladie, and of thyne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,
<pb facs="tcp:15004:38"/>
and of thy heauenle aduocates, they wil reddilie geue thee ſuccour, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture appearing vnto thee in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouing &amp; gratious ſhapes, ſodeynlie from their preſence euery deuiliſh viſion wilbe gonne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule.</note> THE fourth rule of the arte to dy wel, that ought to be obſerued in tyme of ſickneſſe, is the election or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion of two or of one faithful &amp; wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued companion or freind, eyther ſeculer or religious, which in the end of thy lyfe may be preſent with thee, and aſsiſt thee; whoſe office ſhalbe princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally about three things.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that hauing committed the charge of thy ſoule vnto ſuch, in this extremitie they wil make thee ſome ſpiritual exhortations, comforting and perſwading thee to patience and conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, to the end thow mayeſt haue the greater reward in heauen for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming thy ſelf to God his holy wil &amp; pleaſure, in this and euerie other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction. Alſo they ſhal exhort thee,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15004:38"/>
that all care and all loue of tranſitorie thinges of this world ſet a ſyde, with all thy hart thow bee attentyue to the health of thy ſoule, thanking our lord God continually for his innumerable benefites beſtowed vpon thee. Secondly that whileſt they aſsiſt thee, they do make thee many good and profitable demaundes. Firſt they ought to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund, yf thow firmelie beleeue all the articles of the chriſtian faith, and that our holy mother the Churche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeueth and holdeth, moreouer they ought to aſke thee yf thow haue greef and ſorrow for all thyne offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt God, aſking pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with an humble and contrite hart, and yf thow purpoſe neuer to offend him more, &amp; yf for his loue thow willingly pardoneſt all thoſe that haue offended thee. And they ſhal alſo put thee in remembrance, that yf thow haue taken away the good name or the goodes of any perſon, that thow actualy yf it be in thy power, do without delay reſtore it. And after they ſhal exhort thee to
<pb facs="tcp:15004:39"/>
put all thy hope and ſet all thy loue in our moſte mylde and louing redeemer, beſeeching him with feruent deſire, that hee wil giue thee perfect faith, hope and charitie, and that for the merits of his holy paſsion, and for his infinite mercie hee wil giue thee the euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glorie of heauen. And yf the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſhould not to theſe demandes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere like a good chriſtian, then his choſen freindes before mentioned ſhal with all diligence do their endeuour to remoue from him euerie il apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and diſpoſition of ſpirit, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him with louing &amp; ſweet woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, how much it is needful at this tyme to prepare himſelf to receyue deuoutly all the ſacraments of the Churche, and wholie and thorowlie to do according to the demaundes and queſtions aboue ſpecified. To the office of this faithful and deuout freind or freinds, it ſhal alſo belong to prouyde that the ſick do not dy without the ſacramentes, and that the images of the Crucifix and of our Ladie be their in preſence, and ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15004:39"/>
the eyes of the ſick: alſo that their bee holy water, with the which let all the chamber and the ſick perſon be ſprinckled, becauſe it auayleth greatly againſt the power of the deuil. Alſo that their be red the goſpels of Chriſtes paſsion and ſpecially that of S. Iohn, or ſome other thing of the bible, and that hee be put in mynde of the ſaintes, and principallie or his aduocates and patro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to whome in his lyfe tyme hee hath had particuler and ſpecial deuotion, let their alſo be warning geuen, that in the chamber wheare the ſick lyeth their be no reaſoning of worldlie matters, nor lowd ſpeaking, but onely ſo much as is needful for behoof of the ſick, for then is tyme to pray, and not to prattle: alſo that none weep their, that great ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence be kept, and that their be in the chamber no great multitude of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: they ought alſo to prohibite that the ſick perſon be not much moleſted with the viſitinges of his freindes and kinsfolkes, and ſpeciallie when his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:15004:40"/>
encreaſeth, and that there is in him no great hope of lyfe.</p>
               <p>And thus I make an end of this ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d chapter, in the which I haue declared the preparation called the approching, which ought to be made in tyme of ſicknes. And it conteyneth 4. rules: the firſt is called conſtancie or patience: the ſecond deuout receyuing of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Churche: the third a wary and good prouiſion againſt the deuils temptations: the fourth a good election or choyſe of one or two faithful freinds, that may haue diligent care of the ſick.</p>
               <p>And now in a few woordes I wil diſpatche the laſt preparation, decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that which is to be done, in the paſſage and very laſt end of this preſent lyfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:15004:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE THIRD CHAPTER,</hi> wherein is declared in few woordes, the laſt preparation which hee ought to make, that is come vnto the very end of his lyf.</head>
               <p>IN this third chapter, wee are to ſpeak of the preparation, which ought to be made when a man is nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt the end of his lyfe, as when hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to enter into his agony and draweth onward to his laſt gaſpe. This chapter conteyneth foure ſhort rules, the which after the example of our lord Ieſu Chriſte wee ought to obſerue in this laſt paſſage of our lyfe, for wee ought to know, that as the lyfe of our Sauiour hath bene geuen vs for a rule, and for the inſtruction of our lyfe: ſo alſo his death hath bene ſet before vs to teach vs how to dy. Therefore S. Gregorie ſaith that, <hi>Omnis Chriſti actio noſtra eſt inſtructio,</hi> that is to ſay: all the actions of Chriſt are inſtructions for vs. As our lyfe then ſhalbe beſt, when it ſhalbe lyke to that of our redeemers, who was verie man, and verie God: ſo
<pb facs="tcp:15004:41"/>
alſo our death ſhalbe verie laudable and holy when it ſhal haue thoſe conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, which that death of our bleſſed May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had, who being on the hard wood of the croſſe neere vnto death; diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie obſerued fower rules before his bleſſed ſoule departed from his ſacred bodie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule.</note> THE firſt rule was, that ſpoyled &amp; naked hee aſcended the holie croſſe, forſaken almoſte of all, where hee would dy poor; reſeruing no worldly thing for himſelf. So wee ought at the leaſt, now at the laſt, after the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of our Sauiour to renounce ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually euerie ſuperfluous and vayne poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; all worldlie &amp; carnal loue, leauing that to-great affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wee weere wont to beare to wyfe and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, careing no more neyther for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches nor for honours of the world, to the end that wee bee not troobled by any thing: but in this laſte period of our lyf, to think wholy vpon almighty God.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:15004:41"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond rule.</note> THE ſecond rule obſerued by our lord on the croſſe, was, that hee prayed for himſelf, and for his enemies: repeating as he prayed vnto his father, the woordes of the Pſalme, <hi>Deus, Deus meus (reſpice in me) quare me dereliquiſti?</hi> that is to ſay: O God my God (look vpon mee) why haſt thow forſaken mee? and afterward this verſe of the Pſalme: <hi>In manus tuas Domine commendo ſpiritum meum,</hi> that is: Into thy handes o Lord, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſpirit. So ought wee to pray firſt for our ſelues &amp; after for enemies. And at that tyme a man put in ſuch heauines and peril of his ſaluation, ought neuer to ceaſe to cal for help of our moſte mercyful lord God, and of his bleſſed mother, of all the Angels, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, Prophets, Martyrs, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſors, Virgins, and matrons, ſoliciting them with great grones and deep ſighes, to help him in this perillous battayle and in ſo great neceſsitie: and to inuite them that they vouchſafe to accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie his ſoule and guide it into the eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal tabernacles, to enioy the diuine eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,
<pb facs="tcp:15004:42"/>
and to reioyce with them in euerlaſting peace:</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third rule.</note> THE third rule obſerued of our redeemer Ieſus Chriſte; was, that hee with bowing of his head, &amp; in ſuch manner as hee might, took leaue of his moſte deer mother, and of his moſte hartie freindes which were their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent about the croſſe, and recomme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded his bleſſed mother to her new ſonne which hee gaue her. By this hee gaue vs example; to do the lyke, to wit, that when the ſick perſon ſeeth himſelfe to bee neer death, it is very conuenient, that hee recommend his family, as his wel-beloued wyf, and his deere chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to ſome freind that may counſel and help them. After this, all his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants and how ſhold called together, let him take leaue of them, aſke them forgiuenes for the il examples hee hath geuen them, and make them ſome good exhortation. And yf that hee be a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let him giue his fatherly bleſsing to his derely beloued children, ſaying
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15004:42"/>
vnto them: my children yf ye wilbe good, and haue the feare of God before your eyes, your principal and heauenly Father wil neuer forſake yow. Be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent to keep his commaundements, The bleſsing of the Father, of the Sonne, &amp; or the holy Ghoſte, &amp; of our bleſſed Ladie, and of all the Saintes in heauen be with yow. Then taking euery one of them by the hand, and kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them, and imbracing his louing wyf and children hee ſhal ſay: O my deere wyf I pray thee honour and feare our Lord God aboue all thinges, I leaue thee theſe our children, haue dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent care of them: vntil this tyme they haue bene ours, now they ſhalbe thyne: yf thow wilt continew in good lyfe; thow ſhalt neuer wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the help of God. Be of good cheer, &amp; do not not weep, for our Lord wilbe with thee: Then ſhal hee exhort his children, that they be obedient to their mother, and feare and reuerence her as they ought. After this he ſhal take leaue of them all, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:15004:43"/>
them to go out of his chamber, that hee may remayne alone, with his faithful and choſen freindes which are to haue care ouer him euen to the laſt end of his lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth rule. Hebr. 5.</note> THE fourth and laſt rule obſerued of our Sauiour in his paſſage, was, that (as S. Paule ſaith) <hi>Cum clamore valido &amp; lachrymis preces offerens exauditus eſt pro ſua reuerentia,</hi> that is to ſay: offering vp his prayers with a loud cry and teares, he was heard for his reuerence ſake: And the text of the holy goſpel ſaith; that our lord hauing cryed with a loud voyce, and recomended his ſoule to his heauenly Father (ſaying:<note place="margin">Luc. 23.</note> Father into thy handes I commend my ſpirit) yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp his ghoſte, leauing the bodie without the ſoule, wherevpon is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, that our Sauiour hath done three things in this laſt rule.</p>
               <p>Firſt hee cryed with a loud voyce: ſecondly hee wept: thirdly hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his ſoule to his Father, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15004:43"/>
then his bleſſed ſoule departed from his precious and holy bodie. All theſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges ought the ſick man to doe, that is vpon his laſt paſſage, and in the agonie of death. So that after he hath cauſed his parents and frendes to retyre; hauing taken his leaue of them, hee ſhal firſt think vpon the ſtate of his conſcience, and then call vpon almighty God, not with a loud voyce, but with deep and profound ſighes from the bottome of his hart, crauing pardon with moſte ſorrowful teares and intyre contrition, of his creator, for all his ſinnes and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences comitted againſt his diuyne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, let him repent himſelf of euerie ſinne he hath comitted, and with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful hart aſke mercie of almightie God for euerie ſmal negligence, bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly alſo lamenting for euerie litle loſſe of tyme, and requiring helpe of our bleſſed Ladie and all the ſaintes: often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes let him ſay. <hi>In manus tuas Domine commendo ſpiritum meum,</hi> that is: into thy handes o Lord, I commend my ſpirit.
<pb facs="tcp:15004:44"/>
The which woordes the diuynes think to be of verie great vertue: And ſo by meanes of theaſe preparations, beeing filled with good and holy deſires, thow ſhalt come to a happy paſſage of death: and finally re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der thy body to the earth, and thy ſoule to thy creator with whome thow ſhalt liue eternally.</p>
               <p>When the young Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t had heard all theſe rules, hee ſaid to the Ermyte. I cannot expreſſe with my tongue how much your profitable wordes haue bene acceptable vnto mee. Surelie ye haue made me know thinges which I ſhal neuer forget, yea more then that, I ſhal endeuour my ſelf through the grace of God, with all poſsible diligence to put in practiſe and execution all theaſe 12. golden rules of the arte to dy wel, which ye haue declared vnto mee in the precedent chapters.</p>
               <p>But I beſeech yow ſeeing wee be in this talk of death, that ye wil anſwere to certayne doubtes of myne, according to your learning &amp; the opinion of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15004:44"/>
ſacred diuynes, and as ye ſhalbe illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the holy Ghoſte. The Ermite anſwered that hee was verie wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented, ſo that hee did not ſeek to know them of a vaine curioſitie. The Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſaid: I deſire to be reſolued of certayne doubtes, of which the reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and declarations ſhalbe to all men prontable and pleaſing, for their are none which ought not to deſ re and vnderſtand ſuch doctrine, becauſe death is common to all, and therefore ought euerie one willingly to talk and reaſon there of.</p>
               <p>The Ermite then ſaid, my ſonne it is conuenient wee ſit downe, becauſe my great age requireth ſome reſt, as alſo becauſe when wee ſit and repoſe our ſelues, the ſpirits wilbe better diſpoſed to conceyue and more apt to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the anſwere and reſolution to thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundes. Begin then, and propound in few woordes thy doubtes, the Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t then (they beeing ſet downe) began to make his demaundes as followeth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15004:45"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſtion.</note> I Demaund in the firſt place, yf wee be all bound to deſire death?</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered, that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the appetite or deſire ſenſitiue wee be not bound: but contrarie it is in reſpect of the appetite or deſire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable voluntarie and free, vnder which the appetite ſenſitiue ought to be both ſubiect &amp; gouerned. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon heerof is for that according to the opinion of the diuynes, wee be bound to leaue our owne lyfe, and to accept death for the certayne &amp; ſure ſaluation of our neighbour, much more then be wee bound to this charitie for our owne ſaluation, the which wee know for certayne cannot be had ordinarily, yf firſt wee dy not. And wee beeing bound to deſire this laſt and eternal fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity, wee are conſequently bound to deſire all the meanes neceſſarie to the attayning thereof. And for not deſiring of death with reaſon as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, many Chriſtians are da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned, which yf they might, would chooſe to liue in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15004:45"/>
this miſerable world for euer, &amp; would ſay to almightie God; keep thow thy heauen for thy ſelf, for I care not for it, it ſufficeth mee to liue heer with my freindes and kindred. Wherefore it is a thing manifeſt and playne, that ſuch men loue not God. And they haue not charitie, ſeeing they neuer care to ſee his face: wherein conſiſteth all our true and chiefeſt bliſſe. And thus by this anſwere the Merchant was tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowlie ſatisfied: and hee ſaid this was a good poynt, woorthy to bee wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of many worldlings, which are perſwaded they are not bound to deſire death, alleaging that the religious and perfect men be they which are bound to deſire death, and in no wyſe ſeculer and wordly men. But without all doubt they be deceyued, for wee are there vnto all bound indifferentlie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſecond queſtion.</note> THE ſecond queſtion was whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee ought to haue an ill opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of thoſe that dy vnwillingly:</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15004:46"/>The Ermite anſwered, ſaying, my ſonne take heed to my woordes, for in this place I wil tel thee another point, which as I think is of very few vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood. Aſſure thy ſelf it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, to deſire long lyfe, except it bee to make ſome ſpiritual fruit, eyther in himſelf or others: where-fore when-ſoeuer a ſickman dyeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingly, and that hee deſireth the prolonging of hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lyfe principally to other end then to do ſpiritual good, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in himſelf or in others, I ſay that in this caſe hee ſinneth greatly: my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, for that yf hee had the vertues of hope and charitie, hee would more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to bee ioyned with his God, then any other thing that is not in any ſorte giuen or ordayned to that end, that is, the coniunction and vnion with the ſoueraigne good. It is needful then to ſatisfy thy demaund with a diſtinction: wherefore I ſay vnto thee, when a ſick man dyeth vnwillingly, to the end hee would abyde in this world to ioy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15004:46"/>
and triumphe &amp; not to the end to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his lyfe, nor yet to help others: of ſuch an one a man cannot but haue a ſiniſter and il opinion, becauſe it is a ſigne hee hath not charitie toward his creator. But when the ſick perſon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth his lyfe may bee prolonged to do penance for his ſinnes, or to haue tyme to merit more, or to come more in Gods fauour, or els to help others, after the example of S. Paule, S. Martin, &amp; diuers holy men, of ſuch a man (ſo as hee be confirmable to God his holy wil and pleaſure) we ought to haue a good and holy opinion, becauſe hee hath his deſires agreable vnto charitie.</p>
               <p>Hereunto replyed the Merchant; yf this be ſo then are but few ſaued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe few they be which deſire not to haue long lyfe, to triumphe heer in ioy, and to get worldly riches and honours. Therefore theſe things ye tell mee ſeeme vnto mee verie ſtrange and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficil. To this anſwered the good Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myte, ſaying, my ſonne I graunt thee,
<pb facs="tcp:15004:47"/>
that few are ſaued, but yet that which I tell thee is true, and taken out of the doctrine of holy diuynes, which to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyd tediouſnes I name not, nor yet goe I about to proue at length this my ſaying, becauſe it is a thing verie palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and wel knowne to deuout &amp; holy perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third queſtion.</note> THE third queſtion was, whether wee ought to haue an ill opinion of them that at the laſt end of their lyf do loſe the vſe of reaſon, &amp; many tymes do vtter vaine and il ſpeeches.</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered with diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſaying, that of theſe wee ought to ſay as of them which in health become mad, and dy in their madnes, who yf they weare in ſtate of grace, when they loſte the vſe of reaſon, &amp; ſo dyed, they are ſaued: but yf then they wear in mortal ſinne and ſo dyed they be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt damned in hel. And note for our purpoſe, that the iuſt iudge our Lord Ieſus Chriſte ſuffereth ſomtymes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15004:47"/>
ſome great ſinners, in their laſt ſicknes to loſe the vſe of reaſon in iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to the intent that as in their lyfe tyme they haue not bene myndful of almightie God, ſo in their death they ſhould not remember themſeluee. This is that which S. Auguſtine ſaid: <hi>Hac ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maduerſione percutitur peccator, vt moriens obliuiſcatur ſui, qui du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viueret oblitus eſt Dei,</hi> that is to ſay: with this puniſhment the ſinner is ſtricken, that dying hee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth himſelf, which whileſt hee liued did forget almighty God. Such men as theſe hauing liued beaſtly and without reaſon, for their woorthie pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment ought to dy as brute beaſtes; without any good preparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore without confeſsion and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and without any ſigne of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition: oftentymes with blaſphemies and ill woordes they paſſe out of this miſerable lyfe; to the more miſerable and euerlaſting paine of hell. On the contrary parte it happeneth ſomtymes to ſome iuſt and holy perſons, that in
<pb facs="tcp:15004:48"/>
the end of his lyfe, through the great mercie of God, being in ſtate of grace, hee loſeth the vſe of reaſon, and beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth frantick, and ſpeaketh many ſoule and vnſeemely woordes, God who is mercyful, ſuffereth this to fall vnto him for his profit, and of compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the end hee feele not the great payne of his ſickneſſe, and that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils may not haue occaſion to afflict him with temptations, after the loſſe of the vſe of reaſon. God almightie of his benignitie vſeth this mercy with him that hath bene good, and is of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture fearful and frayle, deliuering him by this mean from the grief of the ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which hee doth not feele ſo much when his bodie is without vſe of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: and making him vnable to receyue the deuils temptations, becauſe he that is without vſe of reaſon doth not ſinne. And ſay hee or do hee what hee wil, yea though hee vtter woordes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God in that tyme, it is not impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him for ſinne, but it is inoughe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15004:48"/>
for him whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hee had his vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, that hee had true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trition for his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and was in the grace and fauour of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fourth queſtion.</note> THE fourth queſtion was, whether wee ought to thinke il of them, that dy of ſodayne or violent death.</p>
               <p>The Ermyte anſwered, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the iudgement of S. Auguſtine. <hi>Mors mala dicenda non eſt, quam bona vita praeceſsit,</hi> that is to ſay: That death is not to be eſteemed il, which a good lyfe hath gonne before. Alwayes when a man hath lyued wel, and at the point of death is without deadlie ſinne, ſuch a death ought to bee eſteemed good: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, <hi>Precioſa in conſpectu Domini mors ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum eius,</hi> that is to ſay: precious in our Lords ſight is the death of his ſain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, So as let a man dy of what kynde of death ſoeuer it bee, eyther of fire, or water, or ſwoord, or peſtilence, or poyſon, or ſodaynly, or lingringly, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes his death is ſaid to be holy and
<pb facs="tcp:15004:49"/>
pretious when hee dyeth in the ſtate of grace. Wee haue example of this in many holy confeſſors &amp; martirs, which (in reſpect of the world) haue dyed ignominious and ſhameful deathes; and neuertheleſſe they are now happy with God in heauen. And theſame alſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, to whome as yf hee had bene the prince of thieues, was allotted by the wicked and obſtinate Iewes, the infamous death of the croſſe. And for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie hee ſaith, that alwayes of wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that death is iudged il, when one dyeth in mortal ſinne: although hee haue a quiet and honourable death, to the ſight of the world, and bee in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with almightie God: and alwayes by holy men that death is iudged the wurſt, becauſe as Dauid ſaith, <hi>Mors pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catorum peſsimae,</hi> the death of ſinners is the moſt euil. All deathes then be ill, when men dy in deadly ſinne: and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe euerie kynde of death is good and holy, when a man dyeth in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of almightie God.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:15004:49"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fift queſtion.</note> THE fift queſtion was, whether it be lawful to deſire a man when hee dyeth, that after death hee wil appeare vnto thee, and tel thee his eſtate.</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered, that hee fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to this queſtion two contrarie an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwears giuen by the Doctors. The one is of the Angelical Doctor S. Thomas,<note place="margin">In quodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beti.</note> who ſaith, that when there is not ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned withal any curioſitie or infidelitie, but onely a careful deſire to know the ſtate of him that dyeth, then is it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to require ſuch a thing. The other anſwear co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie; is of Henry de Aſcia, who ſaith that it is not a thing lawful, becauſe it can hardly come but of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vayne curioſitie; and peraduenture of infidelitie, to be aſſured of the lyfe to come, and beſydes that, hee putteth himſelf in peril to be deluded of the deuil, who many tymes appeareth in forme and ſhape of the dead, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealeth falſe things. And therefore wee read in the goſpel, that Abraham would not permit that any reuelation or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parition
<pb facs="tcp:15004:50"/>
ſhould be made vnto the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the wicked riche man, who prayed him to ſend ſome one that was dead vnto them (that yet liued) to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe them of his miſerable ſtate. To whome Abraham anſwered, <hi>Habent Moyſen &amp; Prophetas, audiant illos,</hi> that is to ſay: They haue Moyſes &amp; the Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, let them heare them. But it ſeemeth vnto mee that when a man is not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, neyther of infidelitie, nor of curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, but onely for a ſpiritual conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to fulfil without offence to God, a deſire to know ſuch a thing, that this is no ſinne. Notwithſtanding hold thow that opinion which moſte pleaſeth thee, ſo that thow haue the vertue of humilitie, ioyned with godly and holy deſire.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſixt queſtion.</note> THE ſixt queſtion was, whether hee that hath alwayes liued il, &amp; neuer hath made preparation for death, being now at the point of death, may at that inſtant ſufficiently prepare himſelf to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15004:50"/>
dy. The Ermite anſwered, ſaying, ſonne, ſo long as a man liueth and hath the vſe of reaſon; hee may alwayes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe and prepare himſelf to dy wel. But in truth I ſay vnto thee, that of ten thowſand men that delay it to the laſt inſtant, their is not one ſaued. This is the iudgement of S. Hierome, and S. Auguſtine, and verie wel knowne and manifeſt to other holy doctors, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wil not go about to multiplie wordes in vayne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th queſtion.</note> THE ſeuenth queſtion was, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the deuil do appeare to all thoſe that dy. The Ermite anſwered, ſaying, that ordinarily the deuils ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to all; in the end of their lyues, as may be proued by the authoritie of diuers holy men. The ordinary gloſſe explicating theſe woordes of Geneſes. <hi>Tu inſidiaberis calcaneo eius:</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> Thow ſhalt ly in wayt euen at his heel, ſaith, that this is to be vnderſtood to be at the end of mannes lyf.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15004:51"/>To the ſame purpoſe Eccleſiaſticus alſo ſaith, <hi>Sunt ſpiritus qui ad vindictam creati ſunt, &amp; in tempore conſummationis ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundunt virtutem ſuam,</hi> that is to ſay: their be ſpirits which were created for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge, and at the tyme of conſumation they do ſhew their force: which autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity S. Vincent and other Doctors ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound of deuils that appeare at the tyme of death. And S. Gregorie ſaith, that the deuil ſo much the more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently tempteth a man in the end of his lyfe, as he knoweth hee hath leſſe tyme to tempt him.</p>
               <p>Theſame S. Gregorie alſo wryteth that the deuil in the end of lyfe appee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth aſwel to the good as the euil; yea and that hee durſt appeer to Chriſte himſelf beeing on the croſſe. If then this wicked ſpirit came to Chriſte on the croſſe, how much more boldly wil hee appeere to all other? yf it be not that ſome through the ſpetial grace and priuiledge of almighty God be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from ſuch a diueliſh appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15004:51"/>
as wee read of our bleſſed Ladie, in ſome bookes of ſmalle authoritie, that ſhe aſked and obtayned of her bleſſed ſonne, that at her death ſhe ſhould not ſee any wicked ſpirit or deuil.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The eight queſtion.</note> THE eight queſtion was, whether our Sauiour Chriſte diſcend corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally to the particuler iudgment of all thoſe that dy.</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered, that to ſome it ſeemeth hee doth, and they confirme their opinion with authoritie of holy ſcripture, in the actes of the Apoſtles: where it is ſaid of our Lord.<note place="margin">Act. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſe eſt qui conſtitutus eſt à Deo, iudex viuorum &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuorum,</hi> that is to ſay: it is hee that is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted of God the iudge of the quick and the dead. And in S. Iohn the 5. Chap. it is written: <hi>Pater omne iudicium dedit filio,</hi> that is to ſay, God the father gaue all iudgement to his ſonne. But to ſome other this opinion ſeemeth not credible, becauſe it happeneth that in one and the ſelf ſame tyme diuers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb facs="tcp:15004:52"/>
dy in diuers places, and it is not conuenable that Chriſtes humanitie in one inſtant ſhould bee to this end in ſo many places, and therefore they ſay, our bleſſed Sauiour doth not diſcend per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to giue this particuler iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but rather committeth that office to the good Angel that is giuen vs for our gard, giuing him authoritie as iudge, to end and execute the proces and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to him appoynted, and the Angel, ſo made iudge, condemneth or abſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the ſoule according to iuſtice: and after guideth it to the place aſsigned, eyther in heauen, in hell, or in purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, according as it hath deſerued. But to the vniuerſal iudgment, our bleſſed Sauiour himſelf wil diſcend and iudge the quick and the dead. And in this ſence they expound the authoritie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aleaged.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The nynth queſtion.</note> THE nynth queſtion was, whether our Sauiour Chriſte appeare at the hower of death generallie to all men, good and il.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:15004:52"/>The Ermite anſwered that ſome great doctors haue ſaid that hee dothe, and to approue theſame they alleage the authoritie of Pope Innocent the third in the ſecond book, <hi>de conditione vilitatis humane:</hi> that is of the miſery of man, where it is ſaid that all men, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel good as bad do ſee Ieſus Chriſte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſoule go out of the bodie. The good to their great conſolation and the euil to their great confuſion, to the end that by ſuch apparance they may be aſhamed to haue loſt through their negligence the precious fruit of their redemption. And albeit this bee the opinion of very famous doctors yet do I not fynde it ſufficiently confirmed by authority of holy ſcripture: &amp; for this reaſon there are others that do not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur in this opinion; though yet very Godly and deuout. About this matter then I wil make none other reſolution, but that I hold for certayne, that our benigne and mercyful redeemer appeareth to many in the end of their
<pb facs="tcp:15004:53"/>
lyues as by innumerable examples and approued hiſtories it may be verefyed, but that hee appeareth to all vniuerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I neyther affirme nor deny.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The tenth queſtion.</note> THE tenth was, whether the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler iudgement bee immediatly after the ſoule is gon out of the bodie, or that there bee ſome ſpace of tyme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſentence of the ſaid iudgement be giuen.</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered, that ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilie without delay after the ſoule be ſeparated from the bodie it receyueth his particuler iudgment, with the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of damnation or ſaluation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the condition of his merits. But verie trew it is, that <hi>Omnis regula patitur exceptionem,</hi> euery rule ſuffereth excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore ſome ſoules after their ſeparation attend a good ſpace before their particuler iudgement be giuen, as wee read of a famous Doctor, of Paris who was reputed a man of holy lyfe, but beeing dead, whyles they made his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15004:53"/>
funeralles in the Churche, hee lifted vp his head as he lay on the beere, in the preſence of many people, &amp; a great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of maiſters &amp; Doctors in diuinitie, and diuers ſchollers, and ſaid, <hi>Ad iudiciam vocatus ſum:</hi> that is, I am called to iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and then layd himſelf down a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, wherevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was ordayned that hee ſhould not be buried vntil the next day, and ſo the day following hee did the like, for lifting vp his head againe hee ſaid, <hi>Iudicatus ſum:</hi> I am iudged. And there vpon his burial was deferred til the third day, when as hee in lyke man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (as twyce before) lifting vp his head ſaid aloud, <hi>Condemnatus ſum:</hi> I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, whereby it is manifeſt, that this particuler iudgement continued for the ſpace of three dayes. Through the which great miracle ſundry doctors &amp; ſchollers left the world, &amp; went into the wildernes, where they began the firſt foundation of the order of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſians; otherwiſe called the monkes of the Charterhows.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:15004:54"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſtion.</note> THE eleuenth queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was, yf when this particuler iudgement is done, and the ſentence giuen; the ſoule be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by and by to the place appoynted.</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered, that the holy Catholike Churche holdeth and firmly beleeueth, that our ſoules beeing depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of our bodies; do after their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ordinarily paſſe vnto the place of euerlaſting ioy or paine, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their merites or demerits. And the reaſon hereof is, for that it is the ſoule that principally ſynneth or meriteth, and the bodie without it cannot ſinne nor merit: and therefore it is not againſt reaſon, that the ſoule without the bodie, receyue eyther good or euil, vntil the day of the vniuerſal iudgement: it ſufficeth that afterward at the tyme of the vniuerſal iudgement beeing vnited with the bodie it be therewith for euer eyther ſaued or dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The ſacred diuynes in the fourth of the ſentences do proue this our Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike concluſion with reaſons, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rityes,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15004:54"/>
and authentical hiſtories: but in this place onely the authority of the ſcriptures is ſufficient for vs, as it apee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in the 23. of S. Luke, where our Sauiour Chriſte ſaid to the good theef, <hi>Hodie mecum eris in paradiſo:</hi> This day thow ſhalt bee with mee in paradiſe; hee ſaid not at the end of the world, but this day. And Iob ſpeaking of wordlings ſaid, <hi>Ducunt in bonis dies ſuos, &amp; in puncto ad infernum diſcendunt,</hi> that is to ſay: they ſpend their dayes in plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and in a mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they deſcend into hel. Whereby it apeereth that whyleſt they bee in their triumphes and ioyes, ſodeynlie in the twinckling of an eye they fall into hel.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The twelfth queſtion.</note> THE twelfth queſtion was, yf all they that dy do ſuffer equal payne and anguiſh in the agonie of death.</p>
               <p>The Ermite anſwered no: as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in ſome olde men which dy eaſily, and alſo ſome that ſeeme to dy ſleeping, and ſome whileſt they bee in
<pb facs="tcp:15004:55"/>
an extaſie or traunce: as S. Auguſtine declareth in his book, <hi>De ciuitate Dei.</hi> Moreouer it happeneth ſomtymes that one aliue and in health doth endure greater payne, then an other in the tyme of his death, and it is iudged of Wyſemen, that oftentymes it is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter difficulty to beare the troubles and miſeries of this lyfe, then dying to looſe the lyfe of the bodie. So as in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; there haue bene many holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors that haue ſuffered more gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous afflictions then ſome martirs.</p>
               <p>Wee may therefore think, that there is no man, who eyther before his death, or at the tyme of his death, or at leaſt after death, doth not ſuffer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsiue grief and great torment.</p>
               <p>When the youngman had wel vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood all theſe things aforeſaid, hee would yet haue propounded other queſtions, but the Ermite feeling him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wearie, aſwel for his great age as alſo for his long talk, prayed him, that hee would bee content to aſke
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:15004:55"/>
him no more, but rather that hee would do his endeuour to put in exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution that, which hee had all read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die tolde him, for woordes without deedes are litle profitable, and to ſuch as haue a good wil to do wel it is not needful to vſe many perſuaſions; but breefly to tel them their dueties.</p>
               <p>Then the youngman with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence and humility did vpon his knees giue thankes vnto the good Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite, for ſo many his good &amp; holy leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; promiſed him to make it apeer, that his long diſcours ſhould not bee vnprofitable and without great fruit, And ſo hauing had his bleſsing took his leaue, and without delay, deſirous to giue himſelf wholie to learne to dy wel, diſtributed all his riches to poor orphans, Churches and hoſpitalles, and forſaking this miſerable and deceyuing world entred into religion, where hee continewed a long tyme, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued the aforeſaid rules, til at length hauing liued long and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly,
<pb facs="tcp:15004:56"/>
hee happely rendred his ſoule into the handes of this creator, to whome bee all honour and glorie world without-end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15004:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
